[Music]
i would like to
uh introduce you to
the viewers as a professor
of neuroscience at the university
college of london
and you've made substantial theoretical
contributions to neurobiology
including the free energy principle
and you're a fellow of the academy of
medical science
past president of the international
organization of human brain mapping
fellow of the royal society of biology
weldon memorial prize and medal for
contributions to mathematical biology
honorary doctorates including one from
the university of zurich
i have to say that's quite impressive
cv that you have there
so i think i'd like to start with a few
preliminary questions and it really is
how in your view as a preeminent
neuroscientist
view the early and late childhood
reading as creating models
or frameworks of images concepts of
ideas
is that something that you have worked
into your theory
um in a in a general way absolutely
um you know if you cast
our job as neonates as infants as
building
models of the lived world and our lived
world
comprises other creatures like us and in
particular when we're very young mum and
dad
and siblings and the like and
then it becomes imperative to understand
a world that is in cultured and
by that i mean things that come along
constructs that
shape that world um and make it
sensible in the sense of making sense of
the world
and language is is probably what you
know that's a post-child
of that um thing that has to be learned
has to be
instilled in your model of the world
and in particular making sense of
diabetic interactions
right from birth you know first of all
just sorting out
whether um your
mom is me or i am somehow different from
mother
am i in control of me am i in control of
mother developing a sense of self
so you know the the act of inferring
that mother is somehow separate from me
another creature like me but not me
upon all sorts of communication or
initially affinity touch
but within months we now have
the machinery of language um and that
machinery
really does fast track that model
learning that
um you know sort of building apt
constructs and models
that you can predict what's going to
happen next and indeed of course predict
what you're going to do next what you're
saying next right
your intentions your propositional
stances and
the like so language then um
you know you just look at a school
curriculum from you know
from the start plays a really central
role
um you know in in scaffolding that model
learning that structure learning that
model building
you know language uh is is a fascinating
terrain and of course
it goes from writing to printing to the
current uh
internet way of which language and image
is combined
on screens and so i think there's been
quite a different
approach and understanding of language
and accessibility to language
uh and has that had an impact in terms
of just the way
our brains now generate models of
reality
is that substantially different than
before the invention of the printing
press
go back to the ancient greeks where it
was all oral storytelling
that's a a really interesting question
um
so i'm just thinking in my mind so from
from my point of view
um your language
is the vehicle that provides
a structure to the narratives that we
bring to the table to understand what's
happening
you're on the outside of our brains
beyond our skulls
and what you're effectively asking is is
the written word
is that point of reference that
consolidation that crystallization
of the the cues and the structure
um instrumental in disseminating
and improving the learnability of these
narratives i think so absolutely yes
yes i hadn't really thought about that
would be fascinating to model that
um you know you know because language
prior to the written word
yeah lives in my head and your head but
once it gets your poppers third
world
um there's a there's a reference and a
continuity there
that i would imagine would be best seen
as
something that is sort of self-selecting
in terms of hierarchical covolution
that enhances the learnability of
language
of language in and of itself enhances
the learnability of your generative
models and your inference and you're
making sense
you know making sense of the world so
yeah so
so in a sense to talk about
communication as a heart of the language
really have to i guess look at the
medium in which the communication
has occurred because the to use marshall
mcluhan the media may be the message
uh that the way we construct our models
will depend very much on the boundaries
of that media the amplification of that
medium
and and the way that uh we can use it
for our purposes and purposes of the
community
yeah yeah uh i mean that speaks this
notion or a notion of
a shared narrative you know if i if i'm
using my model of the world
to understand you and make sense of you
effectively if i assume that you've got
the same kind of model that i'm using
then our narrative is is literally a
shared narrative it's it's it's
you know it's not mine nor yours it is
something that we're sort of
um committed to together so that's
your that shared narrative
um is something that we have to aspire
to
and learn together so your it is defined
cooperatively again in an uncultured in
an uncultured way
and the modalities and the shared
commitments to the way that we use
language
whether it's in print or indeed you know
you one could even argue that
mathematics
is uh you know a kind of language
that only works because there's a shared
commitment
to using this modality these
shapes these kinds of sensory cues to
enable me to infer what you are thinking
and what you're going to say next
the uh the other preliminary thing i
wanted to raise is i've been fascinated
because i've seen a number of your
interviews particularly about the markov
blanket uh which is probably would take
a whole show just to go through that
and i'll let you introduce what that
concept is but whether
the kind of generating models that we
get as a child from our reading
experience
could it be said that those form a kind
of markov
blanket in a sense
explains to me cognitive biases a
cognitive bias
are the defenses against basically
contrary or hostile
images or thoughts or ideals or
principles
and so we have a cognitive bias we have
for example confirmation
bias we look for those
articles those books those peoples that
confirm
our beliefs and values yeah no i think
that's that's an excellent point yep
uh i mean you know cognitive biases you
could actually read as
as sort of um base optimal biases that
they you know
so if you subscribe to the free energy
principle
that rests upon markov blankets you are
in the game
all of us anything that exists is in the
game of securing evidence for our own
existence which just means
evidence for our models of the world so
you're going to seek out
confirmation and if you're successful in
seeking out
confirmation evidence that you exist and
you've got a good model in the world
you exist for longer so it's almost
tautological
truism that what you've just said is is
absolutely right
one of the things that you were i heard
you i say in
another interview and i love this in the
context particularly of fiction and
novels
if you are constantly surprised you've
had a bad model of the world
so in a way you you can judge
the cognitive equipment that a person
has how it's been
shaped by how surprised they are
so i i guess the wider your reading is
as a child in many different genres
and styles and periods the less
surprised you're going to be
when you see something because the
range of activity that would have to
surprise you would be
vastly greater yes no absolutely
in fact um we actually use
um measures of surprise as
um measured by uh electrical brain
responses from people with autism or
schizophrenia
um uh you know just to do just to get a
physiological handle on this so you're
absolutely right
you know people do actually use surprise
or oddball responses to sort of
phenotype
um various conditions uh where people
may have difficulty inferring what's
going on
going going on around them so
uh but you you also um bring to the
table the breadth of reading the
um the different kinds of
outcomes and exchanges with your
environment
cultured or not and will certainly
shape and be essential um in determining
the shape of the model that you're you
know
that you're um you take forward into
later life
and if you have a um a
model that generalizes to different
situations that you can
predict synthesize in a way that renders
it
unsurprising when sufficient information
has been secured
then you're certainly going to have a
better model that is more context
sensitive
and will underwrite a longevity in a
changing world or a very
context-sensitive world
i'm just wondering where uh again
getting back to uh reading books and
fiction in particular
where imagination and creativity fit
into your view of
modeling uh and generating models
because although you may be surprised
surprise
for example if you're an improv musician
is actually a good thing yeah you can
riff off of that
so that you you in a sense you invite
the surprise
and when you're writing fiction uh in
some ways you're looking for the
surprise
because that's what the reader wants the
reader is looking to be
surprised because if it's just all
predictable they say the book is boring
yep and another another excellent point
and
a key issue in the philosophy of the
free energy principle which
rests upon something called the dark
room problem you know if we just want to
minimize surprise why don't we go
and seclude ourselves in a dark room and
stay there forever and then we'll never
be surprised um
but that sort of kind of misses the
point um
if we are curious creatures that are
always in the compelled
to resolve uncertainty then the
resolution of surprise or expected
surprise as a consequence of our actions
um is going to be one of the primary
drives
uh for surprise minimization so we have
to look for the opportunity
to minimize surprise so we listen to
stories we watch
um tv series we read books
because we know at the end there will be
a denouement there will be a resolution
of uncertainty
and if you read uncertainty's expected
surprise
you know there's going to be a wonderful
opportunity for that aha moment
when you've your surprise mathematical
kind of surprise
is actually is actually resolved and i
think it's a great explanation for music
you know that you set up an
uncertainty sure in terms of the way
that this rift could go or you know
what's going to happen in the next few
bars and then you're
compelled to continue listening actively
listening in order
to resolve that uncertainty but it's a
resolution of
uncertainty that drives novelty-seeking
and curious behavior
and i repeat if uncertainty is expected
surprise a resolution of uncertainty is
a minimization
of this mathematical kind of surprise
right so
one one of your papers i would certainly
recommend uh
that viewers have a look at is in
neuroscience and biobehavioral reviews
november 2020
issue it's a brilliant paper that
looks very closely at the whole notion
of
generating models and
the commitment of the brain as this
constructive organ that we are
constructing
models and testing them against reality
at every stage and when somehow the
model isn't quite
working well as i understand from the
paper
this then we go into a question and
answer
what are we missing in the context of
this thing
why is it a little bit off or is our
model off do we have to adapt it
in order that we see more clearly the
reality that's there
in other words it's not anything other
than we have
low information and what we're seeking
is to increase the level of
information so that we have a better
understanding and explanation
of what happens next or what may happen
next
yeah that is a beautiful summary of the
essence of active inference
absolutely and i think it touches on you
know
the last exchange in relation to you
know why we
are compelled to be curious why are we
curious creatures
and and that it all boils down to this
minimization of um a resolution of
uncertainty
um entailed by our current models and
states of affairs
in the world so how would you resolve
that you resolve that uncertainty by
gaining information
how do you do that in the optimal way
well you you basically
um respond to epistemic affordances you
you know where to find um the right kind
of information it's going to resolve
your uncertainty so you listen to that
news channel you read
that author um you you you you
go to that wikipedia service
so you you you you know what you don't
know
and asking questions querying the world
is the optimal way to minimize your
uncertainty so you can actually write
this down in terms of a
you know an expected free energy or an
expected
surprise and if again um
i ask you to read expected surprise of
as uncertainty minimizing this expected
free energy
following an action following a move on
the world
is um inevitably
compels you to gain the most information
that resolves
your uncertainty about the world and
interestingly of course
the the degree of epistemic
attractiveness or affordance of a
particular move a particular question a
particular query
the choice of things that you might read
and depends upon your current belief
state
it depends upon what you know what you
don't know so of course you could get
bored
when you've been foraging epistemically
and there's no more uncertainty
so then you'd move on to move on to
something else and you know
our work suggests that that sort of
epistemic
motivation that in um neuro robotics for
example is known as intrinsic motivation
just you know
what would happen if i did that
resolving uncertainty
um about the way that the world works
that's probably
much much more important than simple
sort of utilitarian pragmatic
parents like your being rich or um
if you're a monkey getting fruit fruit
drops in
in an experiment so i think that
resolution of uncertainty that
information gain um is underwrites
most sentient behavior in
systems like like us um and
you know not every system needs this you
know viruses
and thermostats wouldn't have this
epistemic but
i think at a certain level when your
genitive model
is sufficiently deep and prospective
and it has to be in order to cope with
living in a world that is constituted by
other things like you that are also very
deep in prospective
you know then you become equipped with a
model
that entertains the consequences of
your action and of course if you measure
the consequences
in terms of what matters then the only
thing that matters is getting down
that expected surprise that expected
free energy which
just is being curious yeah i i
i'm glad you you mentioned the word
curious because
it seems to me that curiosity is not
equally
distributed some people seem to be far
more curious
than others maybe to their darwinian
disadvantage but
there there is a range of curiosity and
i'm wondering if that
correlates with creativity and
imagination
yeah i'm sure yeah i'm sure it does um
you know so technically um what i think
we are talking about here
is in the cognitive neurosciences
something called
structure learning so we're talking
about the structure of our models
um if you're in machine learning and
you're doing
deep learning for example how many how
many layers
would you have in a hierarchical model
if you're
a neurodevelopers developmental
psychologist and you're
you want to know what particular at what
point different levels in the auditory
hierarchy or the language system
come online and what we're talking about
is building
models literally by wiring in different
components
so but you have to know the structure
and of course you can't know the
structure all you can do
is explore different structures see
whether they're fit for purpose
see whether they explain the data at
hand
but and therefore you have to explore
different models and i think this is
where creativity and imagination comes
in
it's the ability to um think about
counter factual
structures in the world you know what
would happen if the world was like this
or we or like that
was counter factuals included these
differential hypotheses
you can then use your sensory exchanges
with the world
or with others or with books to actually
evaluate
one um model in relation to another
literally using the the the model
evidence the evidence that model
inherited
in in the sensory data so that's how
statisticians and people in machine
learning actually optimize the structure
of their models
and i think that's exactly what we do
during neurodevelopment and
and subsequent experience dependent
learning and what would that look like
it would look like
um you know a creature a system an
agent who entertains
in a very creative way different
compositions different structures
different constructs um that could
possibly explain their world and then
testing out the evidence for these
different for these different uh
constructs and if you're an artist the
way that you might do that
is by looking at the reactions of other
people or indeed your own reactions to
something that's now
out there it's being realized physically
in terms of a story or in terms of in
terms of a picture
so imagination would be if you like um
sort of online uh structure learning
and creativity um that allows you just
to
um on the fly moment to moment
just consider different hypotheses about
what's going on now
but exactly the same sort of
mathematical imperative
i think underlies um the building of the
structures themselves
during neurodevelopment and during our
ongoing
um reorganization of of our brains and
the concepts are entailed by by that
structure learning
yeah counterfactuals are interesting and
i'm wondering if that's something that
is taught along with early childhood
reading as well
is that in a way you could say
shakespeare may have had a right
is that you know all life is a stage and
we're all actors on it
and that childhood reading is a series
of scripts
in which you see the human drama
unfolding in front of you
and by understanding that you
understanding what's expected of you
socially you understand what are the
boundaries of behavior what you can
expect from others so
in some ways it prepares you to enter
society because
you don't have to have experience
directly you can experience
indirectly thousands of relationships
going back hundreds of years
and have a whole generative model
of the human condition from that early
reading
so part of it is can you teach things
like counter
counter factuals for example can you
teach your
your child take hamlet put him in
waiting for god all
that god will put him in hamlet
how does it change the story
yeah i think that's absolutely right and
and he started off that thesis with the
notion of scripts
um i think script is you know a very
nice way
of of thinking about the different kinds
of models that are
going to be plausible going to be
allowable um
um when self modeling you know when you
know because the most important thing is
basically
a model of the world a model of the live
world is essentially a model of me
in a particular world so you know most
of the
most of the pressure on early learning
is just finding out you know
um first of all am i separate from my
mother
if i am what bits of the world can i
move
is it you know which bits of my so
distinguishing between my body and
non-body um and clearly as one
gets more sophisticated more skilled
then one develops quite quite
a um sophisticated and
deep literally with hierarchical depth
generative model of me
but of course that entails the kinds of
things that i do
and the kinds of things in this world in
this culture
and things like me do so i think that's
you know um
one way of looking at scripts and that
has to be learned
you know and as you i think you're
you're also highlighting
using culture using culturalism
that brings with these deontic cues
these these counter factuals
that say well you can be that kind of
person or that kind of person
or possibly more relevant in this
setting you'll be that kind of person in
that setting
you'll be this kind of person um just to
give us to
scaffold and to provide priors
your empirical prize we call them
mathematically prized that are
like informed by experience and the
structure learning and evidence
accumulation
that um the shape the structures
that you will entertain um and of course
you know if we are um
99 of our time is is is basically
spent modeling the embodied me in
some transaction or interaction with the
embodied you
then um a lot of these scripts are going
to pertain to the kinds of things
the behaviors the social norms that
would
apply in that context i do emphasize the
context you know i think we can be
different people in different contexts
we can contextualize
our models um sure in the same way that
if i was bilingual
i would contextualize my narrative or
the spoken narrative and
given you know what i thought you would
understand and i would understand
stem from uh from you and having that
context sensitivity
that underwrites the generalization of
one model for multiple contexts
is this context sensitivity so the
greater the latitude
or scripts you have in front of you i
think the more
apt you will be to cope with any new
context
in later life uh you know i i think
stories
you know even down to the level of of of
reading fairy tales with your
bedtime yeah some of the some of the
sort of
um most um caricatured but
but enduring shakespearean um
um memes or structures or scripts
are all there you know i'm i'm i'm a
fairy princess so i'm some sort of
all the grim fairy tales for example
they have
that sort of life structure in them that
i would imagine most people
would be able to identify with one
character
from a fairy story that you know five
years later will be one character in the
in their favorite eni blyton book or uh
you know whatever children
that read nowadays through to uh you
know the political and
other uh dramas that we read and read in
adolescence
so i think that's absolutely right and
probably um
you know there must be a vast literature
in terms of evo diva the sort of
combination of
um development psychology developmental
psychology and evolution so this notion
that
your evolution is just not the selective
pressure
acting upon a person but the person
builds uh is in a particular
environmental eco niche
that is you know again
massively and deeply encultured
um and because we if you like
shape that culture and that eco niche
that
that encultured eco niche um then
um the economy itself now becomes
subject to selective pressure at another
level so there's a sort of nice dance
between the environment
learning about the denizens and the
phenotypes in that environment
and learning about you know learning the
culture of this environment
and they both have to be like be optimal
hand in hand
as as we go forward one of the things
uh continuing on with the uh the idea of
scripts
is that is reading uh
losing its grip losing its grip and
culture and society
as one of the main forces to learn the
scripts
that are the models that are generated
in order to understand
uh a theory of mind of others to
understand yourself and understand the
world
i mean what in your view because a lot
of people now
are reading less they're they're getting
their information from
uh tv programs i mean that's been going
on for 50 years but
with the internet there's a lot more
distractions so that
the kind of scripts that may be uh
taught these days are short
scripts as opposed to book length
scripts that go into some degree of
complexity i just wondered if you could
react to that
yeah i can but i i get to react as a
pure layman i have no professional
insights here
i do know people um um you know who make
this their life
work um and i think it's a fascinating
area
but you know i i'm just going to say
that's a you know
an incredibly engaging point um
especially with the advent of social
media and the
you know the increasing um
potency of adverts mini films within
within 10 seconds now
you're designed to provide extremely
information
rich uncertainty resolving material
precisely tuned for brains that can only
attend
for 10 seconds or 30 seconds even to
you know um synchronizing the um
the cuts and the editing which with the
natural tempo of our eye movements the
way that we
visually palpate the world so so
will that have any material effect on
the the temporal depth of the narratives
and the scripts
that we sort of start to inscribe
in our generative models of you you're
of
um the self of me of different kinds of
me that that could possibly be
um i i i again as a layman
i i i would be surprised if if there's
any
real damage being done to be quite
honest you know um
you know there's long stories with with
the long term
new months are still intensely
attractive from an epistemic point of
view and and in terms of identifying
with characters and the like
um so there is there is ample evidence
that
people still want the long stories um
unfortunately it may not be and you'll
have to ask me why i say unfortunate
um but um unfortunately it might not be
the
the textual story uh but certainly if
you look at things like game of thrones
or your french police dramas or season
one
of you know the next hbo um
you know mega mega drama series these
these are structured long
narratives um which people um
which people are still um find
um unavoidable and you know and will
commit to
so you know in terms of of um
there being a sort of sea change in um
you know short sharp fast trivial
not trivial but um you know fast
narratives with early closure
scripts with early closure i'm sure that
there is there are lots of opportunities
to
indulge in them but on the other hand
there's plenty of evidence i think that
what people actually commit to when they
settle down
especially during the coronavirus
pandemic um
you know to to do that to go through
their box sets
the box sets are i think an
epitomization of the long
stories and of course the best box sets
are those
that translate in an easily digestible
form
the best books so you know yes
more optimistic than one might think
from a lay perspective
well i i i think i i appreciate you
sharing that i'm just
curious as to whether it might have
implications for your own mapping
pro program and your own notion of
generative models because
the way we generate models depends on an
input and if the input is a book
you're going to generate one class of
models if you're
playing say computer games which uh i
don't have anything against i think it's
actually
those they're fun but you're generating
a different kind of model making
about the world and
those those do make a difference because
as you say
communication is a shared activity
and they're in a reading culture you
share the activity although you read
alone
you share those books intellectually
with
those around you in your culture if that
culture starts to shift then you're
sharing them with a smaller group of
people who model
according to books as opposed to say
playing computer games
yeah i think that's an excellent point
um and
you know one aspect of that point um
brings us to um an important sort of
paradigm
shift um at the end of the 20th century
which was towards sort of
an embodied perspective an inactive
perspective a situated perspective
on sentient behavior which
tries not to to deny the key
role of the physical way in which we
sample our information get our
information from the world
and indeed you know on some radical
accounts
the very physical and embodied
act of sensory you know soliciting
sensory information from the world
could be read as as perception so i
think one one attractive
example of that is the
the finger fluency that teenagers now in
fact millennials now have in terms of
being able to type
on on on an iphone now i don't have an
iphone
so i just don't have this fluency but
they
they will have a substantial part of
their motor and pre-motor and
supplementary motor area
devoted to this fluency which um
you know that would parallel um parts of
my brokers area problem zero 44
that i devote to using more my favorite
words
you know when writing them down so there
will be physical
differences in our motor compensat our
communicative
acts that will be written into
and entailed by different brain
structures and different fluencies
so i think that's absolutely right um
you know
so the new authors may may not now be
people who are writing books they may be
people who are engineering games
yeah sure and so there's more money in
that than there is writing books
um i can attest to that
well if you just want the money then
well that may or may not be a good thing
uh you know it um the question is that a
good thing or or or a bad thing from an
evolutionary perspective
you know you know i make no judgments
but it certainly is a
reality um you know
that you could reverse engineer if you
gave me a young person's brain
from 2015 relative to a young person's
brain
in 1915 there will be structural
differences and if i understand the
nature of their
genitive models entailed by their brains
i will be able to say that
this is the kind of uh you know
youngster who
um who reads books and uh you know
um and i will be surprised to see um
gross differences between you know all
of their friends
uh you know in their conspiracy or their
in group
whereas the millennial um
subject would have a different kind of
brain who would have different kinds of
fluencies
and you'll be able to see well this is
the kind of
new reader who probably does engage in
narratives by watching
um netflix or playing games online with
their with their
you know with their friends and siblings
so as a neuroscience you could see
uh same territory but different maps
yeah
yeah yeah yeah the way it comes
you can see the the mapping uh has been
of a different kind and different
quality but
the territory is recognizable but the
map
of the various trails and where you're
going
is take some use to getting used to
because you don't have
that part of your brain which has looked
at that kind of map before
yeah you don't have that sort of
physical language you can't
articulate and if you can't articulate
if you can't do
then you can't see you can't understand
uh
you know so so you know the essence of
um understanding others um
is this the notion of this shared
narrative
which means that if i see you doing
something
then i can use my models of the kinds of
things that i
do to infer what you intend
and so if i if i can't do something
um then i can't understand
i can't make sense of um
of you if you did the thing that i
cannot do
um so i you know that's not a sort of
mystical statement
you know it really really does um
bite hard say neurology where
people with parkinson's disease may have
difficulties
adopting certain facial expressions or
responding swiftly in terms of
initiating
certain kinds of movements which means
that they can't do it
but crucially they can't recognize those
kinds of actions as commutative acts in
other people
so you just lose the language so i could
never
in any true way understand what a finger
thumb flip flicking duster on the tube
is is trying to do because i just don't
have that
as part of my generative model so i
can't model them
they are another species for me i mean
you know
not in any malignant way but you know
they are now a different generation
and i am not part of that generation
there will always be a communicative
barrier
uh which is not a bad thing but there
will always be that
be that barrier simply because they have
a different way of expressing
i think it comes to the notion which um
you you you you brought to the table
around about the modalities
you know the modality um does
um entail the kind the physical ways in
which we communicate in which we
which we share narratives um and you
know if i don't have
i don't speak that language or i am not
able to uh play a particular computer
game
or i am not a subscriber to netflix
there is going to be a you know a
fundamental
um disaggregation segregation
uh of of different cultural groups um
you know
being generational or or clinical
literally no longer speaking the same
language which is often
the way a generational divide is is put
there's a a breakdown of communication
because the medium in which
communication is used is
it's just different enough it's just
like if you hear a dialect
uh even in your own native tongue you
still have to strain a bit you may pick
out some words but there'll be other
words which are not
familiar to you if you go to edinburgh
you're going to find
maybe in a pub there that there's
someone you're missing some words
uh which are common to everyone there
but are not common for you
yes no absolutely yeah and you know
the dialect is very interesting because
you know that
introduces a degree of uncertainty so
you know
if you just think about what things are
we attracted to and the valence of
things and if the the key imperative is
indeed this
um imperative to resolve uncertainty
then the uncertainty induced by what did
she say
you know right it starts to become
slightly aversive and and and
it is that kind of noisiness that that
sort of
uncertainty which you which irreducible
uncertainty
which you will ignore and you'll go to
another more reduceable kind of
uncertainty
yes this is my kind of book this is my
kind of story this is
you know this this is this is a tv
series
for my age group because i understand
what's going on
and at the end i will get that new month
i will resolve that uncertainty
but if you infer you never you know for
example
um you know new kinds of uh popular
music
that just do not you don't have a
genetic model for you can't predict
what's going to happen next
you'll actually kind of find them quite
immersive because they do not afford the
opportunity
to resolve uncertainty to improve your
model of the world
um you know in any meaningful way uh
and you you you'll you'll you'll you'll
stick to as you get older you will
certainly stick to
the kinds of uh sources of information
that do
have that epistemic affordance so i mean
there
there is kind of an emotional uh
homostasis that i think that people
naturally drift too
so if there's something that is
incoherent
not particularly understandable or
pleasant they either
avert their eyes or pretend that they
didn't see it
this this is part of of human nature
of what you choose to see and what you
choose not to see it goes back to john
burger ways
of seeing and
again i think that comes from from
reading which i think is a segue in
let's go take a time machine back to
york
you're now about 10 years old none of
the medals
none of the accolades or the fellowships
are there
you're a boy reading a book tell me a
little bit about
the that environment in which you are
reading a book
um it's an environment that is shaped
very much by
my family particularly my my parents
really so
i think to to understand um that
environment
um and the books that i would pick up
and read um um you had to understand
the why those books were there so my
mother was
was was um a nurse um
um and when she got married it was a in
the age where
um it was you know the scripts were that
you sort of
invested in in your in your children as
a mother and the father went
out to work my father was a civil
engineer
um which meant we had to move around the
country very much like an army child to
wear the new
structures he was actually a motorway
bridge engineer
so we had to move around the country and
he spent a lot of time on site
so i had this curious mixture of an
extremely bright
man um with a passion for
um physics and engineering and
an extremely bright mother whose only
focus at that time was
how to bring up children properly and so
she comments lucky loads of um
books on um psychology popular
psychology
uh um for for her
edification and um enrichment
that was nice a nice compliment to my
father's books
which were largely all engineering and
his favorite book
uh was space time and gravitation and i
and i
by sir arthur eddington um and i only
found out about
four years ago um how favorite that book
was because
apparently when trying to court my
mother when they're
in their teenage years he'd made her
read it as well
that had to be true love
[Laughter]
because it's the only book on your list
you have seven books
i i i've never heard of this book so i
did a little bit of research
the the most recent review i could find
was in the bulletin of american
mathematical society january
1921 and the only place i could find
to buy a copy was walmart canada's
website
for 89.40 it also said
the other two pieces of information it
had no reviews
and two it was almost sold out
so please tell me what age
you read this book your mother read it
as a teenager
how old were you when you read this book
i'm i'm
it would have been i must have been
about um 10 or 11 years of age
several times um um but it was it was
it was um at a time where we're actually
having maths left
lessons at school so so the narrative
the language of maths was starting to
to emerge um and um
so so i'm surprised there were no
reviews of it because
it was um you know i think latterly
it's seen as a classic in the sense that
it was the only accessible
way that an informed
sort of early 20th century
layman could get a good handle on
general relativity and einstein's
notions so
sir arthur eddington the the author um
was was famed really from for being able
to translate
einstein's ideas into a way that um that
enabled
people like you and me to you know to
grasp the essence of it
um and it's still i think a very
readable um
readable book if you want to understand
the uh you know
not only what is relativity but uh
general relativity but also
um you know how you might take those
baby steps conceptually and possibly how
einstein and people at that time were
thinking
and in thinking out of the box and you
know
logically arguing themselves to the way
that this world must be so
coming back to some generative models of
a very grand sort here
certainly in the context of physics so
um
so you know that that was my that was
probably my favorite
um favorite book because you know it
really did
have that epistemic affordance that we
were talking about it really did
um not only engender a whole
space of counterfactuals about the way
that the physical universe
could uh could work but
also provided a denumont in terms of
resolution of uncertainty so the big
thing about
the story that that book tells
which is basically a story of um
conceptual exploration in terms of the
you know the the
way that the physical universe might
might be structured
but it was written by somebody who was
actively involved in securing the
evidence for it
um his 1919 expedition to
off the coast of brazil for the eclipse
absolutely so i mean it was a great you
know in terms of science history it must
be
such an exciting time for
scientists who also were explorers and
adventurers
it was an adventure story as well as
an exploration of science is that what
really kind of hooked you on
science uh at 10 years old was this book
yeah i think so i mean i think as as
with most um
people who subsequently became natural
philosophers or natural scientists
uh you know in the victorian sense
um those opportunities to find out how
things worked
um again had this epistemic affordance
that was irresistible
and that particular book just just took
you to the edge um and
you know if you ever have the chance to
read it you you will
you will see that it actually starts off
with exactly
um something that we we've already
focused on
as a fundamental way of engaging with
the world which is questions and answers
yeah if if the purpose if we are here
in virtue of being curious creatures um
then what does that mean it means that
we basically seek answers
and how do we do that in an informed and
efficient way
we have to ask the right kinds of
questions so questions and answers
um you know are central to
model building and then living in the
world
and interestingly space time and
gravitation
starts off with a conversation that is
just a series of questions and answers
between behind you know from and between
three protagonists with slightly
different perspectives on the way the
world works
you know mathematician and the physicist
and so on and
so he actually starts with with just a
conversation
uh so you can and that's what i meant by
you know
it was a fascinating insight into the
way that people
were asking their questions and offering
answers
some correct some incorrect um at that
time
but it really pulls you in as well
because you will be wanting to ask that
question
and you want to hear what the answer was
so it was very compelling reading just
just the first chapter
you know and it's a device that i
subsequently used uh when writing with
friends in
uh you know in philosophy proper and
that's the best way to get to the heart
of the matter you know to sort of
get into the narrative through a series
of questions and answer
but then the adventure as you said the
the practical adventure of going off and
doing these experiments
you know uh and the history of
experiments that
underwrite this you know this particular
um
view of the world which was very
different i mean that's something very
refreshing about
about you know the way that you know
our sir arthur eddington paints a
picture of the universe where
they have different shapes you know well
beyond does the universe have an
edge uh you know what's what shape is it
is it hyperbolic
there's a notion of it at the end of the
edge of the universe even exist
does it close back on itself like a big
circle what about
yeah and it was just so fascinating just
again a little bit like
the other kind of actuals that we were
talking about before the
different ways that it could be which
you you know you'd never imagined
but now you had and once you'd had that
experience of imagining another
another way of looking at things then
that made it easier
just to entertain other kinds of
counterfactuals and of course that's the
mark of a good
scientist a counterfactual is just a
hypothesis the
mark of a good scientist and natural
philosopher is asking the right
questions
by bringing counterfactuals or
alternative hypotheses to the table
and that takes and from
imagination you're going to have
creativity coming out of that
because the more you can imagine the
more you can create and construct
and different models so you're learning
this at 10 years
old uh a book which was read by both of
your parents
that actually was a condition for the
father's
decision to want to marry the mother and
she went along with this
so did this become something you talked
about in the family did it become kind
of a family
uh touchdown the space and time and
gravitation i mean
it has everything all the questioning
and answers the process
of inquiring the world i mean did these
things come up at home
not at all no i had to my mother was
completely non-mathematical
would have told my father off if he
introduced that in family conversation
so no no this is all under under the
cover it was all
implicit um you know
my my father um sort of you know
was a was a great educator but but in
the best way possible in terms of just
providing learning opportunities
so he gave me a slide rule and said how
does that work
and never spoke about it again but i
spent months
working out how a slide rule worked at
that age
so before i ever met the concept of a
logarithm in mathematics i already had
a fundamental understanding of you know
arithmetic and geometric transformations
and the role of logarithms
simply be you know trying to appease my
father because he asked me a question
i never told him the answer and i think
that space-time gravitation was one of
those devices he said
read that yeah it's like a slight ruler
yeah
but i do know i did notice it was
interesting you managed to trace down a
copy
although we never discussed it we do
discuss things now
you know uh you know now he's retired
but not in
not in those days but it is interesting
that after i had read it
um you know several times over the years
uh
before i left home he made sure he got
the book
back and it's his he's coming down
in his favorite bookcase
and he won't let me have it until until
he passes
you know for him it was a very important
book as well but but it was all done
silently no my mother would not have um
find those kinds of counterfactuals at
all entertaining i repeat she was much
more into psychology and ways that
people
thought and think you know so she was
much more verbal in her analysis
um so so
there wasn't discussion of general
relativity around the table right now
i i've heard you say as well that
underlying everything the
the foundation is mathematical uh that
mathematics
is is the place that you start
and then you go up from there to explain
the world and i'm wondering
again if this book space and time and
gravitation
was one of the early influences for that
view of reality of model making
starting with a mathematical equation
yeah no i i
i think that's absolutely true i mean
it's both true that i
um have said and believe that
um mathematics i think is the most
efficacious language
um the best shared uh narrative that we
have
um um that you know
that transcends most other spoken
languages or written languages
um and you know it's unreasonable
efficacy boils down to its simplicity
and it
it's delicate but but um
beautiful structure um so i think you're
as
a vehicle as a way of talking about
ideas and
that ultimately has to be reduced to the
formalism of mathematics
before but i think anybody else will
understand it ultimately
i'm not about now but you know in five
or ten
hundred years time all the great
advances i think
um um you have have
or um can be articulated mathematically
i'm just catching myself there because
of course you know you might argue that
natural selection um was a great
biological idea that wasn't necessarily
mathematically
couched but i think in terms of
making um natural selection work then
you would
um you would certainly then formalize it
in terms of genetic algorithms and
you know you know pricing you know sort
of uh you know
fundamental equations of evolution and
the like which actually are very close
to the same equations that underwrite
the free energy principle in terms of us
as curious creatures making inferences
about the world
right we are inference making creatures
for sure let's turn to the first of the
fiction choices
uh one of my favorite and i think
favorite of many people
1984 by george orwell
uh what age were you when you first read
1984 oh
i i can't remember with any veracity um
i must have been i'm just imagining
where it was it was on the bookcase at
the bottom of the stairs where my mother
kept her favorite books
um and in virtue of being in that house
at that time i must have been about
about about 12 yeah 12 to 13 yeah
tomorrow
okay so you pull it off your mother's uh
book shelf was this a book that you just
devoured over
a day or two or you lingered over it for
a longer period of time
i think i probably devoured it i got i'm
quite a slow reader so now i'm in fact
you know i have to confess
since going to university and since you
know committing to a rather hectic
work orientated career i don't read the
pleasure anymore because i have to
review
scientific papers um and the occasional
book
nearly every day so i just have no space
for for pleasure reading so
but in those days um you know you had
the time and the space to
to do it for pleasure and i probably was
quite voracious in
going through it so you know i my mother
had a collection of penguin classics so
i just went from right to left
i remember that i do remember 1984 as
being particularly
uh particularly compelling uh there were
you know there were other things that
i'll just have to say in the doors of
perception but 1984 was you know it was
quite enchanting and frightening
yeah so i do i do remember that one
quite acutely so i have
gone through it quite quickly um you
know late into the night
under the covers uh kind of uh
stuff what was what did you find at 12
years old that was the most compelling
part of 1984
oh it is a long time ago i'm remembering
this like you might
might remember your a dream and not very
well
so we're talking over half a century
since
since i actually read it um
but the kind of the feeling that you had
can you remember that feeling
that experience yes it was just the
horror of
realizing that my comfort little world
shouldn't be taken for granted
um you know when you know when the veil
was slowly lifted on the kind of world
that the protagonist
um in 1984 had to contend with
um it was you know an eye-opener that
such
societies uh you know uh such um
cultures could could actually exist um
and may actually exist in other parts of
the world i didn't know
at that age so it was just a revelation
that there were other universes
universes of a cultural sort of an
attitudinal sword
are you going back to these these sort
of the norms
that um you know your how should i
behave
in this context in this in this society
so that was that was an eye-opener and i
and you know curiously attractive
because it was just so frightening
uh and you know once you developed this
hunger for
uh another kind of culture another kind
of society
and what you couldn't couldn't do in
that society and all sorts of things
which must resonate with everybody
you know you know all the little phrases
like room 101
double fishing all all of those classic
things which you know whether or not you
like the word meme i think the meme
applies to
to these things that once you've seen
them
uh they stay with you for for life and
so you know
these these were you know every few
pages was an eye-opener
and of course there was always this i
can't know what this is true or a false
or made memory now but there's always
this sort of
notion that he could get out of the city
and you know
and go off to these these green fields
you know and escape with his with his
girlfriend at some point
so i love that as well and i think
that's possibly because
um you know
the way i was brought up in yorkshire
there were two
bits of my life there was sort of hard
work sometimes actually getting used to
being in a new school because
moving around a lot you know settling
into a new
uh new environment and then holidays off
on the yorkshire moors
so i've always had this poncho this this
sort of
um always light reading about um things
like so far from the mudding crowd by
getting out there um back to a quieter
pace of life and i
i just remember that there was this sort
of
um this was this escape
for the protagonist in 1984 if he could
get there if he could realize it but it
was clearly never going to happen in any
meaningful way
that was that was almost again quite
quite attractive
yeah it was not the hobbits in that case
you know this this was a pretty dark
world in uh
that's portrayed in 1984 and what what's
interesting
is it's a book that has endured
for uh 60 70 years now i think it's
about 70 years and it's now out of
copyright 1984.
but let me just give you a couple of
phrases here from
from the book the party told you to
reject the evidence of your
eyes and ears it was their final
most essential command
in other words your ability to do what
you're talking about in your
your paper of asking questions asking
better questions resolving the
uncertainty you no longer have the
autonomy to do
that that has been stripped
from you questions and answers are
over this is the script the only script
there are no questions and we may change
the script
tomorrow we may be at war against these
days or tomorrow
we may not we'll let you know
that's that's the world of 1984 and part
of the horror of that
is another of the quotes
not merely the validity or experience
but
the very essence of external reality was
passively denied by their
partnership there was there's no
generative
uh models uh that are done independently
uh in 1984. uh it
is a chilling book uh
and it's a book that fits into some of
your other early fiction as well
it's it's a statement about power and
those who see seize power never
voluntarily relinquish their power
those were great excerpts i've forgotten
them about it's all coming back now
yes so i was wondering whether you were
going to
um talk about the ghosts of that
withdrawal of our
life affirming and i would say
mathematically necessary
um um quest for evidence for our own
existence
in you know um uh whether whether that
was being recapitulated in the in
in the modern era by things like fake
news
you know in a sense you can imagine fake
news is basically saying the truth does
not
matter obama truth decay there is no
evidence of any worth out there anymore
i think that's equally frightening uh
but you know but painted in black and
white
uh by all well i think that that's
that's imaginative
well again let me give you a couple more
uh quotes
uh to refresh your recollection he's
talking about
the ideals set up by the party was
something huge terrible
glittering a nation of warriors
and fanatics marching forward in perfect
unity all thinking the same thoughts and
shouting the same slogans
perpetually working fighting
persecuting 300 million
people all with the same face
and then power is carrying the human
mind
to pieces and putting them together
again in new shapes of your choosing
again i ca i could perhaps see a 12 year
old
uh are all reading this and some of this
it seems to me now is reflected in your
own research
and your your own modeling is it is a
way to showcase what the human brain
mapping should be it should be have the
freedom
the basic freedom to generate models of
the world
without manipulation without
interference
that there should be some choice in this
and there's george winston with his
girlfriend julia
trying to find some small way
to model a traditional relationship
and being unable to do that being
bounded in in such a way that
the only thing they could do was to
submit
they could no longer question they could
no longer answer but they love
big brother so i think
with 1984 we find
a book where
again curiosity comes up in orwell's
world there is no curiosity that's
allowed
there's no creativity there's no
imagination
and so creativity and imagination go
across just language you go across
music it goes goes across the
mathematics that you use to describe the
universe
because it may disable and disable
institutions that have a vested view and
what the model of the universe
is copernicus this is you had your
copernicus moment
when you were talking earlier about
suddenly i
understood growing up in new york that
york was not the center of the universe
there were things
going on in other places that were quite
terrifying the way to interrogate the
world
was not universal it was local
yes sir absolutely and perhaps that was
i mean you know
looking back clearly you can see that
kind of utopia
is just not sustainable it's everything
sure
so what one way that people um
philosophers describe this sort of um
the ability to um pursue life as a
curious creature is self-evidencing the
you know the existence is just acquiring
evidence
asking questions and acquiring the
evidence for your own if you're in
existence
so you're just mulling over what the
the excerpts that you've you've just um
shared with us
what that is describing is it's
completely unsustainable and it's
frightening because it cannot exist
or if it does exist it won't exist for
very long it is the exact
opposite of self-evidencing that
latitude that creativity
that opportunity to ask questions to
reaffirm and then change my mind about
you know
my place in in this world so perhaps
that's why
it was curiously frightening but as you
say very dark
yeah it's a system but you
a lot of what orwell wrote about in in
the 40s we can see playing out in
various countries today
where there are more totalitarian
measures authoritarian measures to limit
free
expression which again when whenever i
hear
limiting free expression it's limiting
the right to question
question is the challenge the challenge
is is the model may not be right
it needs improvement we need better and
more
detailed answers and that requires
being able to say the current model is
flawed and so you have
millions and hundreds of millions of
people who don't want the questioning
who are quite happy to have the party
decide what the truth is and that
everything else is false
are they happy good question
good question whether that brings some
kind of emotional resolution
maybe it is at just an emotional level
that happiness for them is is having the
security that there is a community of
people
who have faith in a particular
stagnant modeling of the world that the
model
of the world of course probably never
existed because
these are fantasy models but they
believe them to be real
it's not a simile or a metaphor it was
like
nope it was like napoleon saying i am
caesar
not like i am like caesar i am caesar
so there there is that kind of
internalization that can go on
and seems to be going on yes
yes you're attempting us
be into a political discussion of
contemporary no no i don't
i don't want to go there okay but but
you know we we may
uh go there a little bit in terms of the
next uh
book which is quite political homage to
catalonia which is another george orwell
uh this is non-fiction as opposed to
fiction
but it is a absolutely memorable i
remember reading this very young as well
so i'd be very interested how old you
were when you read this
and what what kind of influence it had
on you
at the time and now
so clearly my mother put all her george
l or el um or well penguin classics in
order so
it would have been red next to 1984
and you know that one was
in a similar spirit to um just realizing
the world could be in a different
uh you know in a different way or there
weren't um
there were realizable universes out
there
so you should never take your own world
for granted
what i took from the homage to catalonia
was it
was the autobiographical aspect i didn't
um until you reminded me remember it as
an autobiography
i thought it was just a story about a
young man's adventures
watching the you know a war in in you
know originally
things it started in barcelona but but
the the other thing for me was
um i could see me in 10 years time
and that there were different
possibilities about the way you used
your life
um because i had assumed that i was
going to be a good boy
you know probably thought at that time
that i was going to be a psychologist
because of my father's passion for
mathematics so
you know i probably already had
committed to a life as a mathematical
psychologist or like some kind of
scientist involved
involved in the brain but you know i was
impressed by
orwell's sort of moral and political
convictions
you didn't have to do that you could
just say no i'm leaving this country and
i'm going to go
so just a different way of scripting
your life
was a real thing and it actually
happened and here was this elegant
young man talking about how you know how
he chose to
to spend and risk his life um you know
at a time you know when we well i was at
school i have to make choices about
exams and the kind of education and the
career path that you you
that you were likely to pursue and
clearly those sorts of questions really
did not bother george orwell
you know he was out there doing doing
the right thing uh
you know having adventures he left eaton
and went to spain to join the uh
partisans there
i mean one of things i love about orwell
and it comes out in homage is his
humility
is beware of my partisanship
my mistakes are fact and the distortion
is inevitably
caused by having seen only one corner of
events there's there's a a
beautiful sense of humbleness
in that statement because you know
anyone who's been in a situation
uh like that knows that what you're
seeing is not the whole context
things that are going on or orthogonal
to you are multiple you have no
knowledge of them
and so what you're what you're reporting
on is what you've experienced and what
you've seen
and there are very few people and orwell
was one of them who was able to
acknowledge
i could only tell you what i experienced
what i
saw and i can also tell you beware
of the propaganda from abroad written by
people who have never been here
who have never been in battle have never
seen the things that go on
because they have an agenda yeah
one one of the things that uh is
interesting about homage as well
is his humor arises
i love this quote for some reason
all the best matadors are fascist
i i think you know i've been thinking
about that maybe it's
it's the public display of the power to
slaughter the bull
in front of uh a stadium filled full of
people
that would be attractive uh there is a
certain level of fascism
in the matadors role and performance
a wonderful play of language and the
thing with thorwell is he's able to
layer
his observations with these kind of deep
insights by just the right metaphor at
the right time
so orwell also uh
in addition to his reporting on the war
had things to say about the
uh the ruling class in in england i'm
just wondering as a young boy growing up
if that uh had any impact at all
here's a quote on class whether the
british berlin class or wicked or merely
stupid is one of the most difficult
questions of our time
and at certain moments a very important
question
i think it did it did influence me um i
mean
it's difficult to say whether those
books
influenced me or whether i have chosen
those books
because i have i have subsequently
um adopted a particular political and
world
view um but i suspect the former um
you know interestingly your point
about your beware um the
um being partisan on the basis of of you
know the secluded amount of
of evidence that you gather from from um
you know from your exposure to the world
having you know
in contrast um i
probably inherited a lot of my political
views
not obviously from my parents yeah but
also
by just assuming that orwell was right
um
so you know i subsequently grew up to be
effectively a socialist
uh of an understud understated sort
but if i had to commit to one side of
the political divide or another i'd
certainly be
um in in almost a direction uh simply
because i i i took him at
face value because of the honesty and
the integrity of his writing
um both the fictional writing but also
the you know
you know what struck me you know him
writing about you know
his own experiences as a you know as a
young man
yeah i mean you're absolutely right i
mean that
autobiography uh is
an excellent example of honesty brutal
honesty
and you know he talks about when he was
shot
he says two things went through his mind
first his poor wife what was she going
to do her husband's
killed now in spain he says my second
thought was
this is just crazy this is stupid this
is some
random shot of i'm standing in a trench
i'm not being heroic or anything
i'm just shot talking to someone it is
absolutely beyond my comprehension that
i'm going to
die in this stupid pointless senseless
way and all the nurses and all the
doctors said the same thing
anyone shot through the throat they
always die
you didn't die you are the luckiest man
alive so there's orwell saying
you know what there is an amongst the
absurd
there's also random luck
i had both that day the absurdity of
being
shot in the place i was shot at the time
uh along with the fact that i survived
when i shouldn't have survived
i forgot about that but now you've
reminded me yes that was a very poignant
part of yes thank you
again i think going back to
generating models is
and again it's generating models and
uncertainty go together
in in this way is that there is a degree
of randomness and chaos
and luck that's involved and
you find that some reading as well that
basically a character can have
some either good luck or some battle
things are happening
outside of his or her control
and whether homage to catalonia is one
of those books
i think there's there's something to be
said
that there is a certain degree of
random spin the wheel of you end up in
spain as opposed to portugal or
thailand or wherever and
things happen there that would not
otherwise have happened to you if you'd
gone another way it's the counterfactual
again
so what we're learning then from your
reading list is there are a lot of
counterfactuals
that the characters and the authors are
talking about
yeah from eddington to to orwell so
maybe there's a lesson here
that delicious diversity yes
the diversity the the counterfactuals
continue to proliferate if you allow
them inside of a creative imagination
found in the right series of books
which leads us to lateral thinking which
is a non-fiction book
by edward de bono what
what was your age approximately
about 30 um so this was the
the um this is one of my mother's books
you know a whole series of popular
psychology books but i remember that one
in particular um
[Music]
simply because it drilled down
possibly in the sort of popular
psychology fashion
um on how we thought and in fact it
actually addresses
exactly the other sort of the model
building the creativity
um so the natural thinking you know
could be read as just
thinking outside the box gaining access
in your head
to that diversity those counterfactuals
you know that sort of enable
you to render your understanding your
narratives your model of the world
generalizable and context sensitive so i
i can't remember very much about it but
i do remember being intrigued
by the importance of
um letting go of preconceptions and
um celebrating the brain
as literally a fantastic organ a
generator of fantasies and hypotheses
and
counterfactuals to to enjoy itself
in thinking about different ways of
solving problems or
explaining explaining this and that and
it's certainly something which
um you know became
a scientific question in later life you
know thinking about how how on earth do
you get a computer to do this if you
wanted to
simulate aha moments of insight
in silico you know what your
how would you engineer that what you
know what are the principles that
underwrite that kind of
that particular sort of creativity and
imagination
and resolution so you know sometimes
it's it's the creativity is almost
paradoxically
finding simple solutions you know past
emotions explanations oh it's just like
that
deflationary uh your explanations
so you know i got a sense of that from
from what i remember of
um sure of developers edward
natural thinking for me
i read it quite young as well is it some
ways it was kind of a
simulation program of surprises of how
to surprise yourself
and in some ways it's like
test crashing a car to see what gets
bent
see what works what does it how you can
make it a little bit stronger and better
and so forth
and that lateral thinking was that way
of
testing the model that you have
and you test it in hard ways that
surprise it
because you know no model has all the
answers
that at some point there's going to be
model failure and what you're looking
for is
how best and most efficiently to get to
that
failure of a juncture and to learn from
that and
by improving the model go back through
the process
and it's in basically an indefinite
process because the model never gets
totally perfected
yes that's that's
one of the things i think i i took away
from that book when i'm well
that that's it i i you know i i've
forgotten that aspect but you're
absolutely right and
of course that is exactly the structure
learning we were talking about before
you know testing against the evidence at
hand breaking the model
reassembling it adding little bits in or
taking stuff away
that is exactly the sort of you know the
um the
the thing that underwrites how we learn
to live and
live in this world uh so so that so
technically that would also be known as
bayesian model selection where
those hard tests of your hypothesis your
explanation
are essentially seeking out
data that would disambiguate uh between
the hypothesis of the right model this
is the wrong model right so
you know good informal formative data is
often the data
the evidence that destroys your
hypothesis
breaks your model that road tests your
car
in a destructive way then you know that
was wrong and then you move on
to something which is you know so that
i hadn't seen got that perspective i
haven't remembered that perspective but
it's it
he does feel absolutely right you know
from a
first principal account of sentient
behavior you know
because in some ways it i mean de bono's
book on lateral thinking kind of
underlies
the process of scientific thinking which
sets it apart
and maybe it's that kind of process
that's difficult to communicate to a
non-scientific
audience because to think there are
people who are trying to break their
models
in a world where most people are trying
to protect their models
at all costs you see that they're
talking cross-purposes
yes that's a good point yeah um
so you know you know if i was lecturing
students in psychology or physics i mean
you know the whole point of a good
experiment
is it provides definitive evidence for
or against your hypothesis
so good data is data that will actually
enable you to move on from a particular
hypothesis so
there's always there's always a
counterfactual in science is the
null hypothesis and the alternate
hypothesis and what you want and those
data that allows you to disambiguate
if you get some data you left 50 50 you
that's a bad scientist
again it's just another way of saying
asking the right questions
so what is a question it's just a move
on the world
to solicit some data which resolves your
uncertainty
you know i think that's a lovely
description of the scientific process uh
which you know begs the question um
you know what what what instances of
people trying to protect their model or
their ideology
um you know is is that part of this sort
of uh confirmation bias and
bay's optimal maintenance of a
particular generative model
maybe you know you know
if you can find the right environment in
the right
and the environment or the culture
permissively provides the right evidence
perhaps that's a viable solution
as well but of course then you take away
this context sensitivity
this counter factual richness that we
were talking about before
you can't generalize you know that 1984
utopia will work
provided everybody commits to that and
there are no external
perturbations there's nothing else in
the universe that's going to
come along and undermine it or
recontextualize it
i think and again uh your markov blanket
is a useful
metaphor in this case where if you have
one that is so thick it's impenetrable
it can't be
changed it's not subject to question and
answer
it is the titanic it will never sink
uh as opposed to i think the scientific
process
markov blankets are like the universe it
can be in
multiple shapes and configurations and
some
we learned from better explanations are
better shapes than others
but no one has the right to say one is
the preferred the only shape
yes no absolutely yeah so i was just
thinking about um
a very thick mark off blanket i'd never
heard that before but it's a lovely idea
which of course would would render you
completely insular you know are you
isolated yes you're very thick
and you're immutable unchangeable
um and provided that thick blanket
protected you from the rest of the
universe
that will be fine but of course the
universe is going to be around that
blanket at some point
yeah then you get this sort of you know
this dynamic
so it's a very good point from the point
of view of physics because the whole
point of the markov blanket
is that we're not islands you know we
have to exchange
with the world outside our heads the
world outside our communities
and if you're a cell the world outside
your cell boundaries
um we are open systems and that does
require exactly this sort of
transformation and transf mutation
and dynamics and reshaping of the markov
blankets that
separate me from not me or you if i'm
not you
it is it did occur to me in your uh
earlier
conversation with me that there might be
a range of these markov
blankets and that
there may be an element of the
population where that
that blanket is so overwhelming
it can't be changed in the other end
it's so fragmentary it is easily
destroyed
either of those are not going to be
reproductive
of a happy life of a life that's
rich with texture and able to
accommodate surprise and uncertainty
yeah no that's absolutely right i mean
you can see examples of
of this all around you you know
the mark of blankets that are so friable
so labile so capricious that they
only exist fleetingly um is a very
different
definition of things that dissipate die
and decay
you know so all of those d words which
have negative connotations are just
descriptions of the dissipation of the
markov blanket
a thing losing its thinness uh you know
as a markov blanket disappears
so stuff that doesn't exist or decays or
dies or dissipates very quickly
that's one end stuff at the other end
and can exist but it exists like a stone
or a diamond
for as long as it is allowed to exist
and does absolutely nothing
and it's the goldilocks regime in the
middle
where we live which is not a stone
uh but neither is it neither is it a
forest fire
yeah let's go to the lord of the rings
uh it's interesting you mentioned you
know growing up
in uh the countryside uh
in york and that you know uh as you
probably
know j.r.r tolkien grew up in
countryside in worcestershire outside of
birmingham
and in some ways the lord of the rings
is
his um
perception of that childhood of that
place
of those people of those times the
culture the myths
and he brought in all of the myths with
the slavic
finnish celtic greek norwegian
he was a great linguist at oxford
university
uh we had the chair there and
these books i think had a profound
influence on
uh multiple generations i know i'm not
certain if they're
read today they than they would have
been in the past
but i'm very pleased to see them on your
your list because uh again we're back
to 1984 in a way we're looking at
symbols of power sources of power
the most powerful people setting
the communication moral
agenda of what people can do what they
can think
and that the power in this case is one
ring
by someone who is power hungry
sardone uh living in his castle
in moldova and
we have a small group
from uh the forest the hobbits
frodo and sam who venture out
on a reverse quest
which is a counterfactual if you like
it's this is not odessa's this is the
opposite
they are at home unlike ulysses who was
trying to get home
so being at home they needed a reason
to leave and the reason to leave was to
take
the ring that bilbo had given photo
his cousin to go back it was only one
place where it could be destroyed which
was the center
of this power and the whole story
is the journey back to mortal
in order to destroy the ring that
threatens to destroy
middle earth which is where the hobbits
live
so how old were you was this on your
mother's bookshelf as well it wouldn't
have been amongst the psychology books
but where was it
this was this is my book so and
and in a different way from 1984
you know i think this is my first
exposure to the
um the fantasy literature um
another world but so this was much more
escapism it wasn't
about having your eyes opened i
recognize everything
uh that you know tolkien was writing
about
whether it was the countryside an
idealized
country your countryside you know
homestead um or the mountains that i was
familiar with with the pennines
indeed with the occasional trips to the
welsh mountains or the building
um or the scottish mountains um
so and also i i can't remember why but i
i also
loved sort of um old english folklore
and
you know the details of of of
sir arthur and merlin and the like and
you know if i could have been one person
at that age i would like to be merlin
as a teenager so but so that all of
these sort of
um notions and and narratives
and the atmosphere um and the you know
the compass of this new world that
that tolkien had created was fit very
very comfortably with all the things
that i
that i love but it was somewhere you
could escape too and
that had all the right ingredients you
know the the
the one ring the simplicity the you know
the
david and goliath uh kind of situation
the uh overwhelming odds
uh the heroic venture with
a small fellowship
and that within this fellowship they
could find the resources
creative resources in order to overcome
what seemed to be
impossible odds yes
you know the hallmark of a great story
will they do it
will they succeed
yeah where uh rather than the uh
george winston ending in 1984 where he
says
i love big brother here
the big brother is in for a fall
and it i mean one of the things i think
that's interesting about
the the lord of the rings is
the symbolism of going back in england
to really pre-anglo-saxon
england before you know certainly before
uh with the normandy invasion that
there was a sense of people living with
nature
as part of nature that really the
the big changes came with the
agricultural and industrial revolution
and that that changed everything that
took
communities away from the force
destroyed the forest
and that was in a sense uh something i
think the token
regretted very much the
the sense of if you want to just that
was the power the new power was these
new technologies
that were coming in and basically
uh changing everything and everyone
so i there must have been changes that
were going on when you were growing
up in york as well uh in
in the rural area you could probably see
even in your childhood
that uh things were not going to stay
the same
yes absolutely well i mean you know my
father was instrumental in that in terms
of building
uh a lot of the infrastructure so
certainly in england at that time
that's when you know a lot of the uh
the the technology and infrastructure
which we you know which we currently
enjoy was being
was being assembled so things were
changing and of course mixed with the
slight um sadness that my father would
have to leave the home to do that
so i didn't necessarily see this
infrastructure building
this the mechanization um um
of of england as as necessarily the best
thing because it entailed
actually the absence of my father said
he's a younger man
but you're absolutely right and you know
another
authorized love was thomas hardy because
it just took you before this time it was
just a much safer time it all
struck me that the past is a much more
comfortable pleasant place to be
because there really is no uncertainty
about the future
because you know what happened um and
certainly in this so pre-technological
setting i've always been drawn to dramas
in an escapism sense stories and and
literature that is in a quieter gentler
more contemplative time usually with
lots of fields and grass
and vegetation
well the the thing about the past is
that it's
basically drained of most of the
surprise because
we know what happened uh and what didn't
happen and there can be
revelations that come up here and there
that change
our idea of what happened and we may be
a little bit surprised by it but
being surprised about a new piece of
information from the past is quite
different than being surprised about
what's happening today or what may
happen tomorrow
to prepare to prepare for i mean just
just to perhaps put this in context at
that time
you know that there was cnd and the cold
war
and i remember you know having um
government information
films at school about what to do in the
in the case of a nuclear explosion so
there's a genuine
fear that the world was going to
certainly amongst my age group
probably naively there was a genuine
fear that the world was going to explode
um and you know you know watching
pictures of nuclear bombs go off
induced the kind of deep exit
existential fear and angst that you have
during a nightmare
so there was you know certainly in the
era of
thomas hardy in wessex or in um
in middle earth you knew that couldn't
be a nuclear bomb
um but there were still great challenges
ahead
you know there was still sort of dramas
and betrayals
and you know so there was still a really
important narrative but it was a
it certainly did not entail the kind of
devastation that industrialization and
technology
and certainly nuclear technology would
entail if it all went
uh went wrong right
at that point in in sort of english
history
yeah it's it's interesting as well
because i know you've written a lot
about you know communication
and the importance of that is that
it's been said of token's uh trilogy
that he's really writing about the loss
of communication between man and nature
that there were lines of communication
and that it
part of what he was trying to do was to
write about that breakdown
the relationship between man and nature
and uh you know with climate change
these days we can see that
actually uh that breakdown has had quite
significant consequences if we
uh could move on to lord of the flies
from lord of the rings to the lord of
the flies i'm not certain if there's any
perfect segue for those two titles but
uh we're going to try our best
were you living with your parents in
york at the time you read this
yes yeah about the same time um
probably a little bit older because i
also remember
doing that at school or at least having
having discussions at school so
obviously i got to the stage of doing my
studies for english literature but i had
read it previously
um and this was um this this was at the
tail end of my mother's collection
um but i think spoke very beautifully to
psychology um and you know the way that
we relate
to each other um you know when
circumstances
when circumstances change so this this
was you know
um portended um
a growing fascination with
psychology and psychiatry and eventually
i became a psychiatrist on route to
um uh becoming becoming a theoretical uh
clinical neuro
biologist so this this was
this was um an eye-opener um
not in terms of the way that the the
world works but in terms of the way that
we work
so for me yeah again very very
compelling read
i mean you read this as an adolescent
and really it's a book about adolescence
without adult supervision
of in a sense dividing into factions
and the factions might be called one
would be
maybe ralph who was more uh of the
for civilization and democracy and
consent
and uh rule of law
and then of course there was jack who
was just the opposite he was
into hunting tactics power games
domination uh piggy who was the
intellect
and the rationalist and simon
who uh was the incarnation of good
and holiness so we had all of the
adolescent characteristics
there uh put together and
from from your observations as a
psychiatrist in the past
was it a reasonably uh
valid look at how adolescents
divide into factions and the kind of
values that emerge from that
yes i i think i think it is and
beautifully painted you know there's
different dimensions and aspects
and also very apt descriptions of all my
classmates
the different classmates you could be
and i have to say almost to you
you had a choice you could become any
one of those people in
in different contexts so again you know
different scripts for
different ways of coping and coping here
in a very changeable unconstrained
context where you were in charge
i mean it certainly um it certainly was
a you know a detailed picture of
adolescence
but in many senses one could imagine uh
grown-ups
disintegrating in exactly the same way
we are without those societal
strat infrastructures and cultural
constraints
in play to keep us all together all you
know on this you know reading from the
same sheet
or him sheet but certainly um
you know as an adolescent um
he was a good
library or repertoire of different ways
of behaving and i
i can remember um yeah wanting to have
mixtures
of of of the you know the key characters
and
you know i was growing up at that time
um having moved
because my father was now building
motorways in
north wales in england so moved to a
different
uh a different school where there were
um a lot of people um where the nearest
city was liverpool
um and some of them were were beautiful
characters very
you know sort of compassionate um some
very religious
some your hard people um
[Music]
sometimes obliged not to be piggy which
was a natural tendency given my
intellectual
leanings so i deliberately tried to be
uh unpiggy
and learned it it took me it took me
about six months to smoke a cigarette
without being sick but i had to do it
get that edge
um so it was you know it was great to
see that
you know to see all these characters uh
on different ways of behaving
um uh you know play out but you know
also how
they all those trays become very much
accentuated
and caricatured in their expression when
the breaks are off
you know when the context and the
constraints are not there
you know all the paranoias come in and
you know the outlandish surprising ways
of responding
um when you can't predict what is going
to happen can sometimes lead to quite
catastrophic
outcomes so that's that's a very
interesting observation i hadn't thought
about that but
you're right it's they have
they arrived with one script but
where they're in an environment where
there were multiple scripts that could
be used
and there were surprise and it's
how they dealt with surprise on
different scripts that led to the
conflict
which is kind of interesting as well
with token who
who's in a sense created the middle
kingdom that
it's filled full of piggies and and
ralph's
but the other characters aren't there
jack is not
there in tokens idealized
communication of man and nature so there
is
there is that interesting juxtaposition
of lord of the flies and lord of the
rings
and one which um i think
certainly um
had more influence in terms of
a scholarly and studied approach to
personal interactions you know
which you know you know i should not
have been surprised you know
roll forward 10 years and i was studying
psychology
university and then subsequently
psychiatry
as a practicing uh practicing clinician
so you know there was a richness there
that was
um possibly underwritten to a certain
extent by reading those
those books and you know
another book i remember was animal farm
around that time which seemed to have
the same sense to it you know that
you know this is this is the the
integration of the psyche at an
interpersonal level
that could be afforded if you're if all
those constraints
don't you know aren't in play or that
harmony that
tolkien was restoring in his long story
and was not was not you know attained
yeah it's uh again you know looking at
those books that we've discussed it
really is a question of
of harmony's juxtaposition with power
and does power ultimately capture
harmony
for its own purposes and defines it in
such a way in an
orwellian way that you have
it has the best of both worlds and
everyone else has a script
which is the worst of all worlds but
it's their script and they believe in it
so there there is i'm glad we're we're
working on this metaphor of scripting
because in a sense what we've been
discussing
uh in this conversation are the various
scripts
that appear in the the literature here
the diversity of them
how in some ways it's the same script
but in
different contexts yes
you know suddenly in lord of uh of the
flies you have
adolescent boys without supervision
in a state of nature what kind of
disintegration
happens and what scripts arise out of
that
catcher in the rye by j.d salinger
an american novel a classic
which is on your list again about an
adolescent going through a particularly
difficult psychological time being
kicked out of his exclusive
school and private school in
pennsylvania
and making his mission
to save all the innocent children of the
world
from going off the cliff through
ignorance or their own innocence so
what drew you to this particular book
that was the book the last book i read
so i've been in
in my late teens if not early 20s then
and um i i can't remember how i came
across it but
you know i i do remember reading it
while traveling and i don't remember
where i was traveling but
becoming absolutely engrossed so that
was one of those books you just couldn't
put down
i don't know why with certain grossing
it was um
it had the same um
the same kind of completeness that lord
of the rings brings to the table in
terms of defining
a complete universe where you're all the
rules are known
nothing is resolved but all the
contingencies are in play and
indeed there was a little map in my
version of the rings you could actually
see where you were
that was bounded um and in the same
subtle way but in a different way um i
think catching the rye had that that
this was you know a little universe
which was i i can't remember now because
it's as i say
more than half a century since many
decades since i read it
but it had that it was is this is a
little island a little bounded island
of a few days in a young man's life
where the earth just got into that
little island that little sort of epoch
it was completely self-contained an
episode and you didn't have to worry
about the you know the
you know the past or the future you just
were in this particular
bounded um critique description
uh adventure within this within this
epoch
and that was very comforting but also
very frightening because again there's a
sense of disintegration
so i probably misread it um
what i what i remember from this was was
and it probably is again a made memory
due to my psychiatric training later in
life but i remember it
as basically uh what we'd now describe
as an early s you know an early
psychotic break
a young man um experiencing the first
psychotic break and disintegration again
of the psyche the
the disconnection of the
the connectivity that ties our world
models together in
inside our head and all the
um the delusional mood and the
misperception or misperception of of
what matters and what's going
on in just daily life and
daily transactions with you know with
relatives and friends and
and teachers and indeed i think one
point ends up in a psychiatric asylum
yeah yeah yeah um so
i remember it acutely because you know
because of course i
within within a few years i was actually
dealing with these
people uh you know students at oxford
university who were
experiencing the early um symptoms of
schizophrenia
going through very similar episodes and
weekends and you know so
it was just a very poignant very
personal
i thought it was almost autobiographical
but you know obviously it wasn't
it read as if it was yeah yeah
again had it had an honesty in its
disintegration and its chaoticness
with which you know you know as a
student
of the way things could go wrong um you
know it was it was
very engaging so it was obviously
influential as well
uh in terms of career path and in terms
of your
your own modeling of the world
particularly adolescence in the world
would be in a way modeled by
holton caulfield and his uh
inability uh to
kind of accept uh a larger reality
there's one quote i'd like to share with
you from from the book
uh which shows the quality of the
writing
and i i think uh the essence of the
story
she wasn't doing a thing i could see
except standing there leaning on a
balcony railing
holding the universe together
that to me is the epitome of great art
putting the mundane with the sublime
the local with the universal the
ordinary
with the meta in one simple
sentence leaning against the balcony
holding the universe together
somehow making that kind of a cosmic
connection between two very disparate
again you hear your counterfactuals yes
put together in
one sentence in order to make a profound
point of the interconnection
that goes on between counterfactuals
and and perhaps that it was that style
of writing and that
beautiful juxtaposition of things which
just could not normally go together
within our sort of
you know our normative appreciation of
the world which made me think it was
autobiographical
i mean to have that ability not
dissimilar to
the sort of lateral thinking and
certainly almost formally identical to
something called
um night's move thinking or um
derailment schizophrenia where things
your things jump about and there are
collisions and juxtapositions and
associations
that are completely implausible in one's
normal internal narrative or indeed
spoke
spoken the kind of the kind of
thing that exactly is the
um required to build new models to to be
creative
so you know i imagine it's kind of thing
that van gogh
had in a visual context
absolutely yeah the the um
the other thing about that particular
example about the balcony and holding
the universe together
is that it has this sort of um
grandiosity of uh
you know which again is a hallmark of
certain kinds of psychosis so manic
depressive psychosis that you know the
the the the the true or false impression
that your your your your existence
your matters in terms of you know
um in a uh you know in a manic sense
omnipotent sense
matters in terms of the existence of the
universe
but also um notice within that
holding the universe together that your
influence
transcends or encompasses the entire
universe a complete loss of boundary
you know there is no boundary between
you and then you get into notions for
your notions of
ego dissolution but of course given our
previous conversation
the dissolution of the markov blanket
yes you're responsible for holding the
universe together yes
exactly the the blanket dissolved but
therefore a fraction of a nanosecond it
exists and you see something you haven't
quite seen before
it's interesting uh that line between
imagination
and schizophrenia where
imagination at some point
along a continuum is no longer
a healthy vehicle to resolve uncertainty
it is a vehicle that's basically
the steering wheel's coming off and the
brakes don't work
yes yeah i think it's a very nice way of
putting it
yep um so i mean just on
logical arguments that that has to be
right in the sense that we still have
people with
this kind of psychosis in our population
so from an evolutionary point of view
that speaks to the fact there is
something very adaptive
about having a schizotypal tendency you
know there's something
that promotes your ability to survive
and to live
in this culture in this world on an
evolutionary time scale
if you've got this propensity for
exploring counterfactuals
but as you say you can go too far so
there's something
you know there has to be something
slightly schizophrenic about all of us
if we're going to make a difference or
indeed
survive in in this world um but the
you know the when it goes too far which
is that gets into the
the which i think
i think holden probably you know
if i read that now and applied so you
know
psychiatric criteria i think diagnosis
there
but it all is all about coming back to
um you know sort of the reduction of
uncertainty
and inference it's all about inference i
mean
you know in a sense what are delusions
and hallucinations if not
simply falsely inferring something is
there when it's
not uh or what is an agnosia
or a neglect syndrome where you you say
you know this is not my arm
or i can't recognize that that person's
face
so that's basically inferring something
is not there when it is
but in both instances it's it's it's a
sort of a disorder of
inference it's you're making the wrong
sense
of the sensory impressions um you know
clearly we have to suspend our
um commitment to the sensory evidence in
order to imagine
perhaps the most beautiful example this
is dreaming so this is
you know something very close to the
heart of uh one of my um
most senior and close colleagues in
consciousness and sleep research alan
hobson
so if you want simple evidence the brain
can
construct its own realities and its own
explanations for the world
then you need to look no further than
dreaming
and that this is you know at the heart
of consciousness
and sentience uh but that sentence is a
cons you know
an active construction that the brain
has generated
where you use the sensory information
during wakefulness at least
to constrain and shape and do do the
structural early a very delicate game
and if it goes wrong
you can easily see how you can fall into
a state of psychosis
um and indeed you can possibly even
understand certain sleep disorders
along those lines yeah that's
interesting i haven't thought about that
but
it makes sense because in a dream state
uh
the input from the world
is is cut off so what is being filtered
in is not
from experience it's from the data banks
of models in your head
that then create their own
counterfactuals
without any kind of countervailing
reality check with the evidence at hand
yes
it's so you can imagine that that's a
nice example every night you put on a
very very thick markov blanket i mean
you can
you know you're successful sleep is is a
thick mark off blanket
one that you can't throw off to cool
down until you wake up it's there
and dreams are the hallucination from
inside
a thick markov blanket
alan hobson would love that i'll i'll
tell him that
[Laughter]
okay so we're coming
then to the uh human condition and
halden caulfield
and catcher in the rye
where let me give you a couple of quotes
to remind you
some of the nice parts of this book the
nature of truth
it's partly true but it isn't all true
people always think something's all true
again one of those leaning on the
balcony kind of statements
the human condition among other things
you find
that you're not the first one who was
ever confused and frightened or even
sickened by human behavior
and that goes back to some of the
earlier books on the list as well
is that realization of the
diversity of behavior and that
there are things that are going on
outside of york
in places like catalonia that i was
never aware of
[Music]
far from the maddening crowd thomas
hardy that's a book i'm familiar with i
went through a stage of
loving thomas hardy read everything
again i think a contemporary of d.h
lawrence in writing
about relationships uh
between the classes and and particularly
in far from the mounting crowd you have
the
the wonderful uh bashiba
and her estate a very accomplished
self-reliant
woman who suddenly decides that she will
risk
everything for a rogue named troy
who really just cast his luck
to the to the the fates and
doesn't really take care of her but
she's willing to risk everything for
this
even though there are people around him
men around her
who wish to court her but she will have
nothing to do with them
so we're seeing uh in a way a kind of
self-destructive
streak uh set in a class setting
what was what was the the book
far from the maddening crowd for you
growing up
it was um it was
in part escapism of the sort that one
enjoys with
um with with tolkien and you know the
other um
you know so great fantasy like uh
stories
um or that inherits from the fact it was
in in past
times so you knew coming back that you
knew there were going to be no nuclear
explosions or walls
so that you know the parameters were set
but within those parameters there was
you know intense tragedy you know i
think that the
you picking up on the self-destruction
um you know
that that that was the tragedy and
certainly in the context of all the men
who who could have made it all right
sure have the self-evident naughtiness
of
of troy was in front of joy
within the parameters of this little
world
um in the southwest corner of
a rural england um we sort of
took on a magnitude which was quite
horrifying you know you just couldn't
believe it was getting worse and worse
and how awful as
troy was particularly from i do remember
feeling very sorry for gabriel
i do remember the opening the opening
thing where he loses his shiva that was
horrible as well because i i used to
have animals i wanted to be a vet at one
point
um so this sort of um getting back to
the yorkshire moors
um aspiration was underneath a lot of
this um
but it was the
it was for me again the perversity
of um a failure to properly
um develop a theory of mind or infer the
intentions
and the nature of another and by
ascribing them inappropriately
the attributes that you would have of
sheba would have had
to to troy she failed to infer what kind
of
person he was and you know unfortunately
had to witness the evidence towards the
end of the story
that she he wasn't the kind of person
that she was
so you know it's a failure of a shared
narrative um in a
in in a romantic and and interpersonal
sort um which you know
is irresistible uh you know as a story
as long as it doesn't happen to me
yeah you know in a way
apart from the maddening crowd you know
the central heroine there
you you can see that the deficiency is
she didn't have appropriate scripts
to model the world of men and what the
capabilities were and what the dangers
were
her motto was inadequate and she was an
unable to ask the right questions
in order to update that model and so she
just got
deeper and deeper in holding on to the
model
she knew even when it was
clear that it was failing her she was
unable to let it go
yes yes yes i mean naivety
um of the sword that inherits from not
having access to those counterfactuals
so had she read thomas hardy she'd been
fine
[Laughter]
he judged the obscure i would recommend
so it uh
the book kind of ends with the world is
largely
made up of compromise and
the the compromise i take that to mean
in a larger sense maybe a little bit
like leaning on the balcony
uh kind of metaphor is that
the compromise is with your ability to
control
the scripts of others and your uh
perhaps inattentiveness in updating your
own scripts
in order to have a more meaningful
effective way of communicating others
what you intend
what your motives are what you wish to
see happen
that was wonderfully important in
particular that notion of updating your
own scripts as part of that
i would say existentially necessary
way of updating your world models
so that actually that word updating
plays a really central
role in formal mathematical descriptions
of model optimization structure and it's
called bayesian belief updating
it is literally um updating your belief
states
on the basis of evidence so you know
this is this is
com if compromise is basically being
able to accumulate and assimilate
evidence in the service of updating your
belief spacing belief updating
in order to improve or optimize your
model of the world
then compromises is if you like an
entirely
and complete description of the way that
we live
yes and and and another one is perhaps a
little darker
is that the compromise of the updating
of your scripts is also dependent on the
power
of whatever mondo you're living under
that somehow the updating isn't equal
across the board
and i think it's important to understand
that culturally that updating process
is viewed in very different ways
and has been done historically
where the power is the environment it is
absolutely terribly
one would hope is not so you won't find
uh you won't find
an orwellian utopia in in wessex though
this is why it's so nice to meet thomas
hardy
[Laughter]
this has been a delightful conversation
carl i
very much appreciate you coming on the
show
and sharing with us your your
in-depth knowledge of science of
neurology of
mapping of the human brain we can go on
for a very long time you've added a lot
the books you've chosen are classic
and i hope that the viewers will
appreciate the insights that you've
brought
to those books and to the general
conversation on
how we use books to model our world and
how that model
influences who we are what we are
what we see and what we want
that was a lovely closure i greatly
enjoyed talking to you
we talked about all my favorite things
thank you
thank you sir you have a great day and
i will let you know when the show is up
thanks a lot thank you cheers